[island music]
[岛屿音乐]
*
[Calypso music playing]
[卡里普索音乐演奏]
[laughter]
[笑声]
- Cha cha!
- 恰恰！
[laughter]
[笑声]
- More fruit punch,
SpongeBob?
- 更多水果潘趣酒，
海绵宝宝？
- You know Plankton,
when you invited me over,
- 你知道浮游生物，
当你邀请我过来的时候
I thought it was another trick
to get the Krabby Patty formula.
我以为这是另一个伎俩
获得蟹黄饼配方。
Now I see you just love
现在我看到你只是爱
social gatherings
in the workplace.
社交聚会
在工作场所。
- Oh, I love
office parties.
- 哦，我爱
办公室聚会。
We've got roller chair races
and karaoke.
我们有滚椅比赛
和卡拉OK。
Hey, I know a gag
we could do--
嘿，我知道一个笑话
我们可以做——
copy our faces
on the new copy machine.
复制我们的脸
在新复印机上。
- Ooh, should I put my face
on the glass?
- 哦，我应该把我的脸
在玻璃上？
- Why don't you lay
your whole body down?
- 你为什么不躺着
你整个身体都垮了吗？
That glass is big enough.
这玻璃够大了
- [grunting]
Blah.
- [咕哝]
废话。
How's this?
Like this?
这怎么样？
像这样？
What about this?
Is this good?
这又如何呢？
这好吗？
- Just lay face down
and keep still.
- 脸朝下躺着
并保持静止。
[grunts]
- Whoo! [giggles]
[咕哝]
- 呼！ [咯咯笑]
- All right, party's over.
Go home.
- 好吧，聚会结束了。
回家吧。
- Aw! But I'd like
some more fruit punch.
- 噢！但我想
再来一些水果潘趣酒。
- No more punch for you.
- 不再给你打拳了。
You don't look so good,
SpongeBob.
你看起来不太好，
海绵宝宝。
I suggest you take
the day off tomorrow.
我建议你采取
明天休息。
- Nah, I feel fine.
- 不，我感觉很好。
- Are you sure?
- 你确定吗？
- You know, now that you ask,
I don't know.
- 你知道，既然你问了，
我不知道。
I think I just felt
a twinge.
我想我只是感觉到
一阵刺痛。
- You'll be fine
if you take tomorrow off.
- 你会没事的
如果你明天请假的话。
[grunts]
[snickers]
[咕哝]
[窃笑]
- Yay!
- Hello, SpongeBob CopyPants.
- 耶！
- 你好，海绵宝宝复制裤。
Can you say,
"secret formula"?
你能说，
“秘密配方”？
- "See-see for-ma-ma."
- “见见妈妈”。
- "Se-cret form-ula."
- “秘密公式”。
- Secret formula.
Secret formula.
- 秘密配方。
秘方。
- [evil laugh]
Yeah.
- [邪恶的笑声]
是的。
[evil laughter]
[邪恶的笑声]
- Now remember, your name is
SpongeBob SquarePants
- 现在记住，你的名字是
海绵宝宝
and your assignment is
to ask Krabs
你的任务是
去问蟹蟹
for the secret
Krabby Patty formula.
为了秘密
蟹黄饼配方。
- My name
is SpongeBob SquarePants,
- 我的名字
是海绵宝宝，
and I want
the secret formula.
我想要
秘密公式。
- Excellent.
- 出色的。
Now off you go.
Wait!
现在你走吧。
等待！
Just keeping track
of my copy.
只是跟踪
我的副本。
- [humming]
- [嗡嗡声]
- [gasps]
- [喘气]
- [whistling]
- [吹口哨]
- What are you doing here?
- Oh!
- 你在这里做什么？
- 哦！
- You said you would
take the day off!
- 你说过你会的
请一天假！
- But I feel great today.
- 但我今天感觉很好。
- Are you sure?
Because you're sweating.
- 你确定吗？
因为你出汗了。
- Ooh.
- 哦。
- [panting]
But you can't work,
- [气喘吁吁]
但你不能工作，
you have
yellow jaundice!
你有
黄疸！
- [laughs]
- [笑]
Oh, Plankton,
yellow is my natural color.
哦，浮游生物，
黄色是我的自然颜色。
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
- [humming]
- [嗡嗡声]
Morning. [humming]
- Whatever.
早晨。 [嗡嗡声]
- 无论如何。
- [humming]
- [嗡嗡声]
Morning.
[humming]
早晨。
[嗡嗡声]
- I said whatever.
- 我说随便吧。
Wait. Didn't I just--
Didn't I--
等待。我不是刚刚——
我不是——
[both laughing]
[两人都笑了]
- Boo!
- 嘘！
- Ooh.
- 哦。
[both laughing]
[两人都笑了]
- There's only one
explanation.
- 只有一个
解释。
I'm still in bed,
and I'm having a nightmare!
我还在床上，
我正在做噩梦！
[groans]
Wake up!
[呻吟]
醒醒吧！
Wake up!
- Hey, I'd like to place
an order for two.
- 嘿，我想放置
两人份的订单。
- Two?
As in two SpongeBobs?
- 二？
就像两个海绵宝宝一样？
Sure.
当然。
This is all just
a bad dream, right?
这一切都只是
一个噩梦，对吧？
I'm dreaming.
You're in my dream.
我在做梦。
你在我的梦里。
- That's me,
the man of your dreams.
- 这就是我，
你的梦中情人。
[chuckles]
[笑声]
- If this is a dream,
there are no consequences.
——如果这是梦的话
没有任何后果。
I can do anything!
我什么都可以做！
Hmm.
Dink!
唔。
丁克！
Huh?
啊？
I really am dreaming.
我真的是在做梦。
- What's your name,
handsome stranger?
- 你叫什么名字
帅气的陌生人？
- My name is
SpongeBob SquarePants.
- 我的名字是
海绵宝宝。
- Wow!
We look alike,
- 哇！
我们长得很像
and we have the same name.
我们有相同的名字。
That's two things
we have in common.
这是两件事
我们有共同点。
[both laughing]
[两人都笑了]
I always wanted
a twin brother.
我一直想要
一个双胞胎兄弟。
How do you feel
about bubbles?
你感觉如何
关于气泡？
- I love 'em!
- 我爱他们！
- Jelly fishing?
- 果冻钓鱼？
- The same thing you do.
- 你也做同样的事。
- How about Squidward?
- 章鱼哥怎么样？
- Oh, "puh-leaze."
- 哦，“噗-莱兹”。
[both laughing]
[两人都笑了]
- I think I'll nickname you...
Me Two.
- 我想我会给你起个绰号...
我两个。
[both laughing]
[两人都笑了]
- Hey, SpongeCopy,
good to see ya.
- 嘿，海绵复制，
很高兴见到你。
Have you learned
the secret formula yet?
你学会了吗
秘方还没？
- Oh, I can't tell you that.
It's a secret.
- 哦，我不能告诉你。
这是一个秘密。
Oh, by the way,
my name is Me Two.
哦，顺便说一下，
我的名字是我二号。
- Me two?
- 我两个？
I'm such a deep sea dope.
我真是个深海迷。
Now that the copy
has come into contact
现在副本
已经接触过
with the original SpongeBob,
he won't tell me the formula.
与最初的海绵宝宝一样，
他不会告诉我公式。
[groaning]
[呻吟]
Time to adjust
my plan.
调整时间
我的计划。
- Wait a minute.
- 等一下。
I can't afford
two SpongeBobs!
我买不起
两个海绵宝宝！
If this is a scheme
to collect two paychecks,
如果这是一个方案
收取两份薪水，
forget about it!
忘了它吧！
You're getting one paycheck
split in two.
你得到一份薪水
分成两半。
both: You are too good to us,
Mr. Krabs.
两人：你对我们太好了，
蟹老板。
- [laughing]
- [笑]
Karen, did you know
you're married to a genius?
凯伦，你知道吗
你嫁给了一个天才？
- How could I forget?
- 我怎么能忘记呢？
You had it tattooed
on my hard drive.
你把它纹身了
在我的硬盘上。
- Now where was I?
- 现在我在哪里？
Oh, yeah, I saved
SpongeBob's digital DNA.
哦，是的，我救了
海绵宝宝的数字 DNA。
- Yay!
- [evil laugh]
- 耶！
- [邪恶的笑声]
- Ooh!
- 哦！
- No, no, SpongeCopy.
- 不，不，SpongeCopy。
We don't put dirty, nasty things
in our mouth.
我们不放置肮脏、令人讨厌的东西
在我们嘴里。
Spit it out.
吐出来。
- Yuck!
- 恶心！
Now, Listen!
现在，听着！
Your name is
SpongeBob SquarePants,
你的名字是
海绵宝宝，
and you're to go
straight to Mr. Krabs
你要走了
直接去找蟹老板
and ask him
for the secret formula.
并问他
为秘密配方。
- Mr. Krabs, secret formula.
Got it.
- 蟹老板，秘密配方。
知道了。
- And stay away
from any other SpongeBobs!
- 并远离
来自任何其他海绵宝宝！
- Got it.
- 知道了。
- Ah, ah,
SpongeCopy.
- 啊啊啊
海绵复制。
- [groans]
- [grunts]
- [呻吟]
- [咕哝]
You see, this is why
I never had children.
你看，这就是原因
我从未生过孩子。
- [gulping]
- [吞咽]
- Yup,
I'm still dreaming.
- 是的，
我还在做梦。
Hello there.
Are you enjoying my dream?
你好呀。
你享受我的梦想吗？
Ha! I heard you liked
your patties ground.
哈!我听说你喜欢
你的肉饼磨碎了。
[laughs]
- [moans]
[笑]
- [呻吟]
- [gasps]
Mister Squidward!
- [喘气]
章鱼哥先生！
Just what the devilfish
do you think you're doing?
到底是什么魔鬼鱼
你认为你在做什么？
- Isn't it obvious,
you red-faced tightwad?
- 这不是很明显吗
你这个红脸小气鬼？
I'm dreaming.
我在做梦。
What's that
under there?
那是什么
在那下面？
- Under where?
Ooh!
- 在哪里？
哦！
- That's right.
- 这是正确的。
[laughs]
[笑]
* I don't care,
I don't care *
*我不在乎，
我不在乎*
* None of this is real
*这一切都不是真实的
Hm.
I always wanted to fly,
嗯。
我一直想飞翔
and since this is my dream,
I'm going to fly!
既然这是我的梦想，
我要飞了！
[laughs]
[笑]
- Hello, Mr. Krabs.
- 你好，蟹老板。
Hey, can you tell me
the secret Krabby Patty formula?
嘿，你能告诉我吗
蟹黄派的秘密配方？
- You want me to tell you
the "formular"?
- 你想让我告诉你
“公式”？
That's quite a responsibility,
laddie.
这是一份很大的责任，
小伙子。
- Secret formula.
- 秘密配方。
- Well, you make
a good point.
- 好吧，你让
一个好点。
Lean in, boy.
靠过来，男孩。
[eerie hum]
[诡异的嗡嗡声]
- He's doing it!
- 他正在做！
He knows the formula!
他知道这个公式！
I can taste triumph.
我能尝到胜利的滋味。
Wait.
No. No!
等待。
不，不！
- Secret formula.
Secret formula.
- 秘密配方。
秘方。
- Hey, look,
another handsome devil.
- 嘿，看，
另一个英俊的恶魔。
[laughs]
We'll call you Me Three.
[笑]
我们就叫你“我三号”吧。
[all laugh]
[全都笑]
Aw, let's go
flip some patties.
噢，我们走吧
翻转一些肉饼。
- Neptune's puddle!
[grunts]
- 海王星的水坑！
[咕哝]
Now that SpongeBob's been
corrupted by the other two!
现在海绵宝宝已经
被另外两个破坏了！
What I need is a legion of Bobs,
a full-on blitzkrieg of Bobs!
我需要的是一大批鲍勃，
鲍勃的全面闪电战！
[military drumming]
[军鼓]
March. March, my pretties,
and learn the formula.
行进。三月，我的美人，
并学习公式。
[evil laugh]
[邪恶的笑声]
[all humming in unison]
[大家齐声哼唱]
all: Secret formula.
全部：秘密配方。
- Whoa, you guys are multiplying
- 哇，你们正在成倍增加
faster than sea bunnies.
all: Secret formula.
比海兔还快。
全部：秘密配方。
- All right, pipe down.
- 好吧，放下管道。
I'm only gonna tell you
the secret formula
我只会告诉你
秘密公式
one more time.
再一次。
all: One more time.
全体：再来一次。
[all humming in unison]
[大家齐声哼唱]
- So you've all memorized
the formula.
- 所以你们都记住了
公式。
Get to work, while I calculate
your paychecks.
开始工作，我一边计算
你的薪水。
all: Yay! Hooray!
全体：耶！万岁！
- They all know
the formula.
- 他们都知道
公式。
- I'll do that.
- 我会这么做的。
- Oh.
Okay, thanks.
- 哦。
好的，谢谢。
- Let me do that.
- Sure.
- 让我来做吧。
- 当然。
- I'll polish
the pickles.
- 我会抛光
泡菜。
- Looks like you sponges
have everything covered.
- 看起来你像海绵
一切都已涵盖。
- Mm-hmm.
- 嗯嗯。
- Hey, you don't
look so good.
- 嘿，你不
看起来很好。
Can I take you home?
Where do you live?
我可以送你回家吗？
你住在哪里？
- I came
from the Chum Bucket.
- 我来了
来自密友桶。
- The Chum Bucket?
- 密友桶？
- * I'm gonna know the formula
I'm gonna know the formula *
- * 我要知道公式
我要知道公式 *
- Plankton!
- 浮游生物！
Me Two says you made him
in a copy machine
我二号说是你创造了他
在复印机中
so that you could steal
the secret formula.
这样你就可以偷东西
秘密公式。
- Well, that's
patently ridiculous.
- 嗯，那就是
显然是荒谬的。
- Uhh...
- 呃...
- You gotta help him.
- 你得帮助他。
I think he's sick
or something.
我觉得他有病
或者什么的。
- I feel funny.
- 我觉得很有趣。
- Me Two!
Me Two!
- 我两个！
我两个！
Oh, what happened to him?
哦，他怎么了？
- I was afraid of that.
- 我很害怕。
I thought I'd save some money
by using cheap toner.
我以为我可以省点钱
使用廉价碳粉。
- What's that mean?
- 那是什么意思？
- It means my plan is ruined!
——这意味着我的计划泡汤了！
All the SpongeBob copies
will fade away now.
所有海绵宝宝副本
现在将会消失。
- Fade away?
All my brand-new friends?
- 消失？
我所有的新朋友？
No, they can't!
不，他们不能！
[crying]
[哭泣]
No!
Don't disappear!
不！
别消失！
[crying]
[哭泣]
- Quickly, man, before you fade!
What's the formula?
- 快点，伙计，在你消失之前！
公式是什么？
- It's easy.
You take one part--
- 这很容易。
你参与其中的一部分——
[grunts]
I don't feel so good.
[咕哝]
我感觉不太好。
- Wait.
No!
- 等待。
不！
You, the formula!
你，公式！
The formula.
公式。
The formula!
公式！
Ouch!
哎哟!
[all groaning]
The formula! The formula!
[全都呻吟]
公式！公式！
The formula!
公式！
[all laughing]
[全都笑了]
- Life is
but a walking shadow.
- 生活就是
而是一个行走的影子。
Ah-loobie-loobie-loobie-loobie-
loobie-loobie--
啊-loobie-loobie-loobie-loobie-
卢比-卢比--
[starts]
[screams]
[开始]
[尖叫声]
all:
Loobie-loobie-loobie!
全部：
卢比卢比卢比！
- What's the formula?
- 公式是什么？
- Well, I did it.
- 嗯，我做到了。
I calculated one paycheck
我计算了一份薪水
down into 300 separate
tiny checks.
分成300个单独的
小支票。
Only one of you left?
你们只剩下一个人了吗？
Here.
这里。
- Ah.
- 啊。
[groans]
[呻吟]
- Sheesh,
what a cheapskate.
- 谢什，
真是个小气鬼。
I can't believe
I failed again!
我不敢相信
我又失败了！
- I can believe it.
- 我可以相信。
- Wait, are you a copy?
- 等等，你是复制品吗？
Quick,
what's the formula?
快点，
公式是什么？
- Well, you see, it's--
- 嗯，你看，这是--
Nice try, Plankton,
but I'm the O.S.--
不错的尝试，浮游生物，
但我是操作系统——
the Original Sponge.
[whimpers]
原来的海绵。
[呜咽]
I can't believe
they're all gone.
我不敢相信
他们都走了。
- Oh, you wouldn't want
all those copies of you around.
-哦，你不会想要的
周围所有那些你的复制品。
They were all just imitations,
anyway.
都只是仿制品，
无论如何。
- Hey, those imitations
were my friends.
- 嘿，那些仿制品
是我的朋友。
- One SpongeBob is more than
the world can handle anyway.
- 一个海绵宝宝不仅仅是
无论如何，世界都能应付。
You're a unique snowflake.
你是独一无二的雪花。
- Yeah.
Thanks, Plankton.
- 是的。
谢谢，浮游生物。
Things did get a bit out of hand
with all those me's around.
事情确实有点失控了
和我身边的所有人。
- Yeah,
you're pretty annoying.
- 是的，
你真烦人。
Well, you can stomp on me now
if that's what you want.
好吧，你现在可以踩我了
如果这就是你想要的。
- Plankton,
I am unique snowflake,
- 浮游生物，
我是独一无二的雪花，
and snowflakes don't stomp.
They skip!
雪花不会踩踏。
他们跳过！
[laughs]
[笑]
- Well, what do ya know
about that?
- 嗯，你知道什么
关于那个？
No comeuppance.
没有报应。
- Gaining speed.
- [gulps]
- 加快速度。
- [吞咽]
- Increasing thrust,
raising nose,
- 增加推力，
抬起鼻子，
air pressure on tentacles,
触手上的气压，
tray tables
in upright positions,
托盘桌
处于直立位置时，
and...liftoff!
还有……升空！
- Eh, spoke too soon.
- 呃，说得太早了。
Comeuppance
in three, two--
报应
三、二——
- [yelling]
- [大喊]
[both groaning]
[两人都呻吟]
- [groans]
Right on my keys.
- [呻吟]
就在我的钥匙上。
[quirky island music]
[古怪的岛屿音乐]
*